DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宫饭》
It wasn't just a myth, after all!
这果然不只是个传说！
That fallen ancient kingdom actually existed!
灭亡的古代王国真的存在！
This is pure gold.
这可是纯金啊
Incredible.
难以置信
Hey…
那个…
Shouldn't we head back up to the surface once?
我们是不是应该先回地表一趟？
If we want to explore, we should be better prepared.
做好更周全的准备再来探索比较好
Stop talking nonsense.
你在说什么傻话？
Senshi,
先西
are you sure you have iron flowing in your veins?
你体内流着的真的是铁浆吗？
Don't push yourself.
不用勉强
You wait here.
你就在这等吧
I want gold too!
我也想要黄金！
I was terrified of being left behind, so I lied.
因为害怕被独自留下 所以老夫说了谎
That place just didn't sit right with me.
我觉得这地方不对劲
And although many of my group were ambitious from the start,
即使伙伴中很多人都野心勃勃
they were acting weird then.
他们那时的表现也很反常
Their eyes were gleaming in the dark,
大家的双眼在黑暗中炯炯发光
and they kept plunging deeper and deeper like they were being pulled in.
仿佛被什么吸引般不断向深处前进
Then suddenly, it began.
然后那件事突然就发生了
What happened?
发生什么事了？
A-A monster!
是魔物！
A giant bird monster showed up out of nowhere
一只巨大的鸟怪突然出现
and took out Totan!
然后杀了图坦！
This isn't just some old ruins.
这不是一个普通的遗迹
It's turned into a dungeon!
它正在转变成迷宫！
By the time fear had jolted everyone back to themselves,
当大家因恐惧而回神的时候
we realized we'd lost our way back.
已经找不到回去的路了
What if we've been trapped in here?
我们该不会被困在这了吧？
All dungeons have a way out to the surface.
迷宫一定都连着通往地表的路
Let's keep our cool and hunt for that exit.
冷静下来找出口吧
We kept roaming the dungeon, avoiding any monsters.
我们避开魔物 不断在迷宫中徘徊
Curiously,when we became thirsty, we stumbled upon springs.
奇妙的是当我们觉得口渴时 就会有泉水出现
When we were exhausted, rooms would pop up for us to rest in.
在我们筋疲力尽时 就有供人休憩的房间出现
Some even got tempted by a gorgeous woman in the shadows.
甚至有人在阴暗处 受到绝世美女的诱惑
Eventually, our food ran out.
后来我们吃完了所有食物
If we keep going like this, we'll starve and die.
再这样下去 我们都会饿死
We must find something to eat, even if it means fighting.
就算要战斗 也得去找些能吃的东西
Something to eat?
能吃的东西？
Even monsters must feed on something.
那些魔物一定也是靠吃些什么来维生
Invar, Brigan!
英帕、布里甘！
Use your shields to be on guard.
你们持盾戒备四周
Null and I will fend off monsters with our weapons.
奴鲁和我用武器击退魔物
Senshi…
先西你…
You stay put and work on mapping out this area.
就留在这里汇整这一带的地图吧
Let's go!
我们走！
That bird monster showed up again!
那只鸟类魔物又出现了！
That damn thing flies off too fast.
那个混蛋总是马上就会飞着逃走
I-I'll join you on the next food hunt!
下次我也要一起去找食物！
No, you'll just slow us down.
不用来 你只会碍事
We've found food.
我们找到食物了
Here, have this.
你就吃这个吧
Even though I wasn't exerting myself, I still became hungry.
明明什么都没做 但肚子还是会饿
I felt so pathetic.
我当时觉得自己实在太没用了
Our daily hunt for food became more urgent than finding the exit.
我们拼命寻找的东西 从出口变成每日果腹的食物
The bird kept on our tails relentlessly.
鸟怪在背后对我们穷追不舍
With each fight, our numbers dwindled.
每次对战都有伙伴牺牲
Finally, with nothing else to eat,
在我们再也没有东西可吃后
we had to resort to killing our horse.
我们最终连马都杀了
That four-legged eagle… there's no mistaking it.
那只四脚鹫…绝对不会错
It's a monster called a Griffin.
是叫狮鹫的魔物
Why is it so fixated on us?
它为什么会如此仇视我们？
It doesn't seem like it's hungry or anything.
看起来并不是因为饥饿啊
It probably just enjoys the thrill of the kill.
它应该是在享受杀戮
They say monsters are like that.
据说魔物的本性就是如此
Don't worry.
别担心
Next time it swoops in, we'll roast it whole and feast on it.
下次它再来 就把它整只烤来吃
Here. Be grateful to Anne and eat up.
来 好好感谢安努 然后多吃一点
What's up with you,
你到底想怎么样？
giving the biggest portion to the useless brat?
竟然让那个没用的小鬼吃最多
He's only 36 and still needs to grow.
他才36岁 还在成长期
As grown-ups, it's our duty to take care of him.
我们身为大人 有责任要照顾他
We can't afford to do that!
我们哪有那种心力啊！
It's over for us when we can't look after the next generation anymore!
要是连下一代都照顾不了 我们就真的完蛋了！
I'm so hungry.
我好饿
If iron really does flow through my veins,
如果流在我体内的真的是铁浆的话
I wonder if I can munch on rocks.
石头应该也吃得下去吧
Hey!
喂！
You've got a hidden stash of food, haven't you?
你藏了食物对吧？
Stop it! What's gotten into you?
住手！你在做什么？
That brat!
这个臭小鬼！
Let's discuss this outside.
我们去外面谈吧
You're scaring Senshi.
你吓到先西了
-How many times do I have to tell you? -Why you! Shut up!
-究竟要说几次你才会懂？ -为何要这样做？闭嘴！
The shouting kept getting louder.
他们互吼的声音越来越大
I heard the sounds of scuffling and a few screams.
中途我听到好几次 激烈的打斗声与惊叫声
Then, it went eerily silent.
然后周遭陷入恐怖的寂静之中
What happened?
到底发生了什么事？
Where's Brigan?
布里甘呢？
Stay put!
乖乖待在这里！
Don't look outside.
别往外看
We were attacked by the Griffin.
我们被狮鹫攻击了
I took down the Griffin, but Brigan died instantly.
我杀了狮鹫 但布里甘当场就死了
When I looked at Gillin's head,
我看到吉林的头后
there was a dent in his helmet, like it had been hit by a blunt object.
发现有一个像是被钝器砸出的凹洞
Let's eat the Griffin.
我们来吃狮鹫吧
If we clean it and make a soup out of it,
把那家伙切开后做成汤
we could survive a few more days.
我们就还能活几天
The Griffin soup, just boiled with water, had a gamey smell and the meat was tough.
只用水煮的狮鹫汤 满是野兽的腥味且肉质很硬
It tasted awful.
非常难吃
But I chewed intently
但老夫像是着魔般地咀嚼
and downed it slowly, taking my time.
花了很长的时间缓慢地将其吞下肚
Gillin said he needed to relieve himself,
吉林说他要去小解
and stepped outside unsteadily.
摇摇晃晃地走出去后
But he never returned.
就再也没有回来
I found myself all alone.
只剩下我独自一人
I lacked the courage to peek outside the door,
我鼓不起勇气去看门另一边的景象
and I was unable to leave the room.
没有办法离开这个房间
I survived on the meat that was left
但我一边以剩下的肉勉强糊口
and pored over the maps I had sketched.
一边查看到目前为止画出来的地图
Eventually, I noticed a pattern in the symbols etched on the walls.
我发现刻在墙上的暗号 具有一定的规律
When I finally gathered the courage to step out of the room…
于是下定决心走出房间…
there were no bodies to be found.
结果没有任何尸体
They must have been devoured cleanly by various creatures.
一定是被各种生物给吃干净了吧
Later, I was captured by orcs,
在那之后 老夫被半兽人抓住
and held captive in their settlement for some time.
成为了俘虏 被监禁在聚落里好一阵子
But when I tried to communicate with them, they turned out to be quite decent folk.
但在试着交谈后 意外发现他们人还不错
In exchange for teaching them ancient Dwarvish,
我以教他们古代矮人语为条件
they taught me how to distinguish between edible and poisonous mushrooms,
让他们教我如何分辨 食用菇和非食用菇
and how to handle encounters with monsters.
以及如何对付魔物等技能
And that's how…
我因此得以…
I made it back to the surface.
返回地表上
But after everything that happened,
但只要一想到曾发生过的事
I couldn't find it in me to return to my hometown.
就没有心情回去故乡
So, I lived near the dungeon or in its upper levels.
于是便在迷宫附近或浅层生活
Eventually, the city on the surface connected with the dungeon,
后来地表的城镇与迷宫连接
and many adventurers began venturing down.
大批的冒险者来到此地
What weighed on my mind
一直让我惦记的是
was whether the meat I consumed truly came from the Griffin.
当时自己吃的真的是狮鹫肉吗？
Every time I eat, I'm haunted by the taste of that soup.
我每次吃东西都会想起那碗汤的味道
No other monster tasted anything like that.
没有一种魔物的肉尝起来是那种味道
That's why I fled from the Griffin.
这就是老夫逃离狮鹫的原因
I'm afraid of discovering the truth.
老夫害怕知道事情的真相
I had no idea…
原来经历了那种事
Senshi…
先西
Then why not try eating that Griffin?
那要不要来吃吃看那边的狮鹫？
-Huh?
-什么？
I mean, it's awful for him
我只是想说 人生还这么长
to be haunted by that memory every time he eats for the rest of his life.
每次吃饭都会想到那件事就很吃亏
If it tastes the same, he can put his mind at ease.
如果是同一种味道也能就此安心
And if it's completely different,
若是完全不同的味道
well, it's a shame, but at least it won't plague him anymore.
虽然很遗憾 但能消除你心中的负担
It's going to plague him even more.
反而会加重吧
What's with him?
那家伙是怎样啊？
What do you think, Senshi?
你觉得呢？先西
You're right.
你说得对
I should try it.
我该吃
Senshi…
先西
All right then!
好！
Let's recreate the cooking as closely as possible.
那我们就尽可能以当时的方式烹调
We'll cut out the meat without doing much to it.
不做太多的处理 将肉切下来
Since the upper body and lower body might taste completely different,
上半身跟下半身可能味道会完全不同
we'll take cuts from both.
所以两边的肉都要切到
You just want to eat it.
你只是想吃而已吧
That's some impressive muscle.
肌肉好结实啊
It's not a carnivore for nothing.
真不愧是肉食性动物
Why did the Griffin pursue Senshi and his group so relentlessly?
为什么狮鹫会对先西他们 如此穷追不舍呢？
It might have killed people, but it didn't seem keen on eating them.
它就算把人杀了 也没吃他们
They had a horse though.
他们当时带了一匹马
Maybe that's why.
是因为这理由吧
Griffins have a penchant for horses.
狮鹫很喜欢吃马
But then why didn't it target the horse first?
那为什么它没有一开始就攻击马呢？
No idea.
不知道
I'll get some water boiling.
我要烧水了
The Griffin's weapons are its front claws and beak.
狮鹫的武器是前钩爪及鸟喙
It can't leave a dent on you like you were hit by a blunt object.
如果遭那些攻击 并不会留下被钝器敲打的痕迹
So whatever killed Brigan probably wasn't a Griffin.
所以杀了布里甘的应该不是狮鹫
But what about the other three?
但其他三个人呢？
Just like how we mistook Falin for a Griffin,
就像我们将狮鹫误看成法琳
maybe it was a different monster altogether.
有没有可能是其他魔物下的手？
There are many large monsters with wings.
长着翅膀的巨大魔物有很多种
The Cockatrice, Basilisk, Harpy, Siren,
像是鸡蛇、巴西利斯克、哈比、赛莲
Pegasus, Simurgh, and Roc.
天马、西摩格和洛克鸟
Which of these monsters possesses a weapon resembling a blunt object?
在这之中哪一个魔物 拥有像是钝器的武器呢？
The water's boiling.
水烧开了喔
Do we just let it boil like this?
就这样丢下去煮而已吗？
Should we add other ingredients?
没有加其他配料？
No, that's it.
只有那些肉
It's going to be a bland soup.
这道汤感觉会很乏味
It'd be nice if we had some garnish.
至少做个配菜吧
By the way, you mentioned that the orcs taught you how to distinguish mushrooms.
话说回来 你说过半兽人教了你 怎么分辨可吃的蘑菇
But is this your first time seeing these mushrooms?
你从来没看过那种蘑菇？
Yeah, I've never seen them before.
对 这是我第一次看到
Marcille, I'm leaving the rest to you.
玛露希尔 接下来就交给你了
-Huh? Hey! -Huh?
-什么？等等！ -什么？
You've come this far, and now you're backing out?
你都做到这一步了 却要丢下不管？
So flighty!
太随性了吧！
Fine, forget it then.
算了 那就不做了
This won't help Senshi anyway.
即使做这种事 对先西也没帮助
No, we've come this far, so let me try it.
不 都快做好了 就让我吃吧
I'll accept whatever truth awaits me.
不管是什么结果我都接受
GRIFFIN SOUP (UPPER BODY) (LOWER BODY)
（上半身的狮鹫汤 下半身的狮鹫汤）
It's done.
做好了
This…
这是…
doesn't taste anything like what I had that day.
跟那时候吃的味道完全不一样
What I ate back then must have been…
看来我那时吃的果然是…
You mean…
你是说…
It's fine.
没关系
A weight has been lifted.
我总算能卸下肩上的重担了
Gillin must have wanted me to survive, no matter what.
吉林无论如何都希望我能活下去
I'll carry on with that wish.
我会背负着他的心意继续活下去
Laios, you moron!
莱欧斯 你这大蠢蛋！
What have you done?!
看看你干了什么好事！
Griffin meat is very gamey and tough.
狮鹫的肉有野兽的腥味 而且又硬
More than anything, the aftertaste is just awful.
最糟的是留在口中的余味很恶心
That's right.
没错
Senshi didn't eat Griffin meat that day.
先西那时候吃的不是狮鹫
But it wasn't human flesh either!
但更不会是人肉
What attacked them was a Hippogriff, not a Griffin.
袭击他们的不是狮鹫 而是鹰马
A Hippogriff?
鹰马？
Unlike a Griffin, which has the lower body of a lion,
狮鹫的下半身是狮子
a Hippogriff is a close relative of a horse.
鹰马则是马的近缘种
It likely kept chasing them down because they had a horse.
它会追着一行人的原因 应该是因为他们带了马
Maybe it was curious or in heat.
也许是出于好奇心 或刚好是发情期
Plus, a Hippogriff has a weapon a Griffin lacks.
而且鹰马有一种狮鹫没有的武器
Hind legs with hooves.
那就是它的后蹄
Its kick could tear through metal, leaving a sizable hole.
如果被踢到的话 金属也会被踢出很大的洞
I assure you, Senshi!
我敢向你保证 先西！
If what you had that day was a Hippogriff,
如果当时你吃的是鹰马
then it's only natural it would taste different from this soup.
当然会跟这碗汤的味道完成不同
Thank you, Laios.
谢谢你 莱欧斯
I feel a bit better hearing that.
听你这么说让我安心了一点
Even though there's no way to confirm what a Hippogriff tastes like.
虽然没办法确认鹰马是什么味道
Let's find out then.
那我们就去确认吧
-Huh?
-什么？
Let's compare it to Hippogriff meat.
来实际比较 吃吃看和鹰马肉有何不同
I thought you were going to wrap it up with something like,
“虽然真相未明 但仍有一线希望”
"The truth remains uncertain, but now there's a glimmer of hope."
你这时不是该暧昧地以此做结尾吗？
I mean, where would we even find a Hippogriff?
而且我们到底要去哪找鹰马啊？
Well,
这个嘛
we have a Hippogriff right here!
鹰马就在这附近！
There must have been reports of one in this dungeon in the past.
过去有人曾在迷宫中回报发现过它们
So why didn't we notice them?
但为什么我们会没有注意到呢？
Because we were fighting a Griffin that shouldn't even be in this dungeon.
因为我们和不存在于 这迷宫中的狮鹫战斗
Why is that?
为什么呢？
Because the presence of an accomplice complicated things.
是让事情变得复杂的共犯搞的鬼
An accomplice?
共犯？
Changelings.
就是调换菇
Now that I think about it, that legend comes from your hometown.
说起来这还是你老家附近的传说呢
Ever heard of Changeling Children?
你听过“被掉包的孩子”吗？
It's a phenomenon where children are swapped with monsters.
那是孩子被替换成怪物的现象
A child who goes to play in the woods returns home as an identical troll.
孩子到森林里玩耍 回来的却是外表一模一样的山怪
For a long time, they were believed to be a type of magic.
有很长的一段时间 这被认为是魔法的一种
But recently,
直到近年
it's been discovered that it's the work of these mushroom-like monsters.
事实证明始作俑者 就是这种蘑菇型魔物
Those who step into a ring of them undergo a subtle change.
生物一踏进蘑菇圈内 就会产生一些变化
Once people learned about this,
知道原因之后
they eradicated the mushrooms, and now they're rare.
这些蘑菇几乎全部被消灭 很少能够看到
To think we'd find them growing here.
没想到会长在这种地方
The way the Griffin seized Senshi but didn't eat him.
那只狮鹫袭击了先西却没有吃他
The sharp kick that killed the Familiar.
还有杀死召唤兽的猛烈一踢
It's likely that the Griffin we fought was actually…
恐怕刚才和我们对战的狮鹫其实是…
Let's find out.
来确认看看吧
Place Griffin meat inside a Changeling fairy ring.
把狮鹫的肉放入调换菇的仙女环中
The meat looks different.
肉的外观变了
It's marbled with fat and looks delicious.
布满油花 变得好像很好吃
All right, let's make soup from this.
好 把它做成汤吧
HIPPOGRIFF SOUP
（鹰马汤）
S-Senshi?
先西？
W-Well, flavors can vary depending on conditions and environments,
听我说 食物的味道本来就会 随着条件与环境的不同有所变化
so I wouldn't worry about it…
你不要太在意
No. That's not it.
不 不是的
I've been wanting
我一直以来
to taste this soup again for a long time.
就是想再喝一次这碗汤
Thank you, everyone.
很感谢大家
Thank you.
谢谢你们
Living in this dungeon for a long time has made me realize something.
长年住在迷宫里的生活 让我发现了一件事
This dungeon responds strongly to a person's desires,
这座迷宫会对人们的欲望 给予强烈回应
whether it's wealth, knowledge, or fame.
不论是财富、知识还是名声
It's accommodating to those like orcs who don't seek anything from it.
虽然会宽待那些和半兽人一样 对迷宫无所求之人
But the moment you desire something, it shows its fangs.
不过一旦渴求某物 就会露出獠牙
From now on,
从现在开始
not only will you aim to rescue Falin, but you'll also be searching
你们除了救回法琳这个目标外 还得追寻狂乱魔术师
for the lunatic magician and the Winged Lion.
以及翼狮
The dungeon's response will become even more severe.
迷宫给你们的回应一定会更加猛烈
Still,
即便如此
there are many things I want to teach you.
老夫还有很多事情想要教你们
Will you take me with you?
能带着老夫一起去吗？
Of course!
当然好啊！
Okay, everyone!
好 那么各位！
Let's get going!
我们前进吧！
How are you all feeling?
大家身体状况还好吗？
I'm feeling cold.
好冷
I might not make it.
我可能要不行了
This has to be food poisoning, right?
这怎么想都是食物中毒吧？
I mean, we've eaten all sorts of things.
我们一路上的确吃下了各种东西
But we can't afford to die here.
但我们可不能死在这里
Falin…
法琳…
How long was I out?
我睡了多久？
I feel lighter.
身体感觉很轻
Has the food poisoning passed?
是食物中毒的症状好转了吗？
Good.
太好了
I was afraid that…
一时之间还想说会怎样…
What's going on?
怎么回事？
Marcille.
玛露希尔
Look at me.
你看看
Does my body look strange to you?
我的身体感觉很奇怪吧？
Marcille has shrunk too!
玛露希尔也缩小了！
Senshi, this is bad!
先西 糟了！
Wake up! Sen--
起来啊！先…
W-Who are you?!
你是谁？
What's with all the racket?
搞什么？从刚才开始就吵个不停
Chil…
奇尔…
Chilchuck, sir?
奇尔查克先生？
It looks like we stepped on some Changelings.
依我的推测 我们应该是 不小心踩到了调换菇
H-How is this even possible?
怎么会有这种事？
They transformed a Griffin into a Hippogriff.
调换菇的力量甚至能将狮鹫变成鹰马
They could do this to people.
人类会变成这样也不奇怪
I'm a dwarf now.
我变成了矮人
Senshi is an elf.
先西变成了精灵
Marcille is a half-foot?
玛露希尔变成了半身人？
And Chilchuck is a tall-man.
奇尔查克变成了长身人
Izutsumi…
莞苞则变成…
is a dog.
狗
No, I think that's a kobold.
不 那应该是狗头人
A kobold with cat ears.
是猫耳狗头人
Now,
现在来想想
how do we get back our bodies?
该怎么恢复为原来的身体
We'll have to retrace our steps.
只能照原路回去吧
If we step inside a mushroom ring, we'll be able to revert, right?
只要再踏入蘑菇圈一次 就能变回来了吧？
That's my assumption,
应该是这样没错
but take a look outside.
但你看一下外面
The path has shifted.
路变得不一样了
While we were laid up, I couldn't stop shaking.
当我们卧病在床的时候 我一直在发抖
Are you saying it was the dungeon, not my body, that was shaking?
在摇晃的其实不是我的身体 而是整座迷宫吗？
I'm not sure we can make it back,
虽然不确定有没有办法原路返回
but let's return to the reservoir.
总之我们回储水库吧
The luggage feels really light.
行李感觉好轻
Marcille, I'll carry some of your stuff.
玛露希尔 我帮你拿一些行李吧
Thanks.
谢谢
I'm liking this body.
这身体真不错啊
I can see well in the dark.
就算很暗也看得清楚
I might even be able to beat Namari in an arm wrestle now.
现在的我跟娜玛莉比腕力也许会赢
Chilchuck, how's that body of yours?
奇尔查克 你觉得那副身体如何？
It feels like I'm enveloped in a heavy, transparent, and thick membrane.
感觉像是被一种沉重 透明又厚实的膜给包住
So, your senses are dulled?
你是说感官变迟钝了吗？
Yeah.
对
But it's strangely calming.
但意外地有一种平静感
Oh, and it's also nice to be able to look down on you guys.
不过呢 能俯视你们的感觉真好
Wait, is this door…
等等 那道门是…
Ugh, this is where we were originally headed!
讨厌啦 是我们原来的目的地！
The deepest point, huh?
就是提到的最深处啊？
We intended to turn back, but ended up pressing forward.
明明想要折返 结果还是前进了啊
Someone set up camp here.
有某人在这里扎营的痕迹
It seems other adventurers have been here.
看来有其他冒险者来过
Do you think they might know how to fix us?
那些人会不会知道 该怎么治好我们啊？
I doubt they ventured beyond this door.
我不认为他们进入了这道门
They might have already teleported back to the surface.
他们可能已经用转移术回到地表了 是当时留下的痕迹
What do we do then?
怎么这样？我们该怎么办？
I've been thinking…
我想过了
why don't we continue searching for the Winged Lion like this?
不然我们就维持这个样子 继续寻找翼狮如何？
Huh?
什么？
The dungeon doesn't seem inclined to release us.
迷宫看起来没有要放我们走的样子
Instead of wasting time resisting it, it might be quicker to press onward.
与其浪费时间抵抗这个结果 不如继续前进会比较快
Of course,
没有啦
once we make it back to the surface, I'm sure there'll be plenty of solutions.
只要回到地表一定会有许多解决方法
I'm not suggesting we stay like this forever.
不可能一辈子都要维持那模样啦
That's absurd!
你这笨蛋！
Just because you've become a long-lived race…
不能因为你幸运 获得长命种族的身体就这样…
He has a point.
他说得对
I haven't experienced any inconvenience so far.
虽然出乎意料 但没什么让人感到不便的地方
So what if the size of our ears is a little different anyway?
就算耳朵的大小不同 那又怎么样呢？
Say we press on then.
假设要继续前进
What's the plan for that door?
打算怎么处理那道门？
Everyone's fussing because it won't open, right?
大家吵了半天 不就是因为打不开那道门吗？
Do you think you can unlock it, Chilchuck?
奇尔查克 你开得了锁吗？
Well, it'd need to have a lock in the first place.
说什么开锁？ 它根本就没有锁可以开啊
I think it operates with magic.
这应该是有什么魔法机关吧
I can sense magic flowing through it,
我能感觉到有魔力流动
but deciphering it would require time, equipment, and money.
但解读会需要时间、设备和金钱
Yaad, what do we do about this?!
雅德 我们该怎么办？
Help us, Winged Lion!
救救我们 翼狮！
-Hey!
-喂！
Hey!
喂
Laios, something's sprouting!
莱欧斯 有东西跑出来啦！
Kensuke?!
剑助？
Why is it growing?
剑助是不是成长了？
I thought the bitter cold had killed it.
我还以为剑助 在寒冷的环境中早就死了
The door…
那道门…
Do you think the Winged Lion is helping us?
你觉得这是翼狮在帮助我们吗？
It could be thanks to Yaad.
或者可能是多亏了雅德
We should thank them all the same.
总之先道谢再说
-Thanks, Lion or Yaad!
-谢谢 翼狮或雅德！
There! I thought I saw something move!
那边！刚才有没有东西动了一下？
It's a Gargoyle!
是石像鬼！
Here it comes!
各位 对方要攻来了！
As you can see, Gargoyles are moving stone statues.
石像鬼正如你们看到的 是会动的石像
Striking them will only end up hurting you, so be careful.
就算打到也只会伤到自己 要小心
There's nothing I can do here.
看来不是我该出场的时候
I'll back off so I won't get in their way.
我还是离开以免妨碍他们吧
Huh? Why is it coming after me?
什么？为什么要来追我？
Because you stand out the most!
因为你最显眼啊！
You're big, so you should fight too!
你那么高 也该一起战斗吧！
Don't be ridiculous! I can't--
不要强人所难！我无法…
Chilchuck!
奇尔查克！
It's okay! It wasn't a direct hit--
没事的！他没有被直接命中…
Marcille?!
玛露希尔！
E-Everything's swirling with rainbow colors.
我周围都是彩色的
Is it mana sickness? With just one attack?
是魔力晕？刚刚那一击就变成这样？
This is bad.
这下糟了
Izutsumi, cover Chilchuck's back.
莞苞 麻烦你掩护奇尔查克
Stay!
等等！
No, Izutsumi.
不行 莞苞
Don't move until I say so!
到我给你信号前都不要动
The loud noises and the smell of blood are getting her all riled up.
她因为巨大的声响与血的气味 而兴奋到发狂
If she starts fighting, she won't stop until she's dead.
一旦开始战斗 到死都不会收手
Senshi, grab the pot!
先西 准备锅子！
Senshi? Why aren't you holding anything?
先西？你为何什么都没拿？
Because it's too heavy.
因为很重啊
Never mind. The sword and pot feel much lighter than usual.
没问题 剑和锅子都感觉比平常还轻
At this rate, I can win on my own.
这样就算只有我一个人也能赢
Except…
可是…
how do I put it?
该怎么说好呢？
This body…
这副身体…
is really exhausting!
很快就累了！
Damn, we're going to lose.
惨了 我们要输了
Everyone, get out of here!
大家 快逃离这里！
Senshi, carry Marcille and head behind that door.
先西 你扛着玛露希尔进到门里
Izutsumi.
莞苞
Follow this bell!
去追这个铃铛！
Chilchuck, take this pot lid!
奇尔查克 这个锅盖给你！
Run for it!
要跑了！
Oh no.
怎么办？
This body is seriously inconvenient.
这副身体超不方便的
And there's no going back now.
现在已经没有回头路了
It can't be helped.
这也没办法啊
Let's just hope those mushrooms are growing ahead.
只能祈祷接下来的路上长着那种蘑菇
This is a genuine dwarf relic.
这是真正的矮人族遗物啊
Do those mushrooms grow around here too?
那种蘑菇也会长在这种地方吗？
It's really hot.
好热啊
Maybe we should start cooking.
我们来做饭吧
Now I get why Senshi always starts cooking out of the blue.
我现在终于了解 为什么先西总会突然开始准备做饭
This body gets really hungry.
这副身体很容易肚子饿
I've never seen Namari randomly start preparing food though.
但我从来没看过 娜玛莉突然开始准备做饭啊
Cooking is perfect for self-reflection.
料理是最适合自省的方法
Knead together flour, water, salt, and egg thoroughly,
将面粉、水、盐及蛋揉匀
then let it rest.
静置一段时间
Meanwhile, combine chopped onions and other vegetables with minced meat,
在这段时间 在绞肉中 加入剁碎的洋葱及其他蔬菜
and mix well.
将其拌匀
Shape the rested dough into a long stick.
将静置后的面团搓成长条状
Cut it into equal pieces,
平均切成同样大小
and roll each piece into thin sheets.
擀成薄片
Place the filling onto the rolled-out dough then wrap it up.
将馅料放在薄片上包起来
Keep wrapping.
不断地包
It's strange.
真不可思议
Working in silence is helping me calm down.
默默做菜后让我逐渐冷静下来
Aren't we making too much?
我们会不会做太多了啊？
That turned out really nicely.
包得真漂亮
It's done.
做好了
BOILED HIPPOGRIFF DUMPLINGS
（鹰马水饺）
The shape is familiar, but the smell is totally different.
明明是熟悉的形状 闻起来却完全不一样
It's kind of odd.
感觉真奇怪
No potato or cheese in them, huh?
里面没加马铃薯或芝士啊？
Back in my hometown, we usually fry them.
在我的故乡会拿来炸
-Let's dig in.
-开动了
Careful not to burn yourself.
小心不要烫伤了
Say that first!
说得太晚了！
Is it just me
不过话说回来
or does it taste surprisingly good?
不觉得这异常好吃吗？
Do racial differences affect taste too?
难道说人种也会影响味觉？
No, I think anyone would find this tasty.
不 不管是谁来吃都会觉得好吃
It's strange, isn't it?
真是神奇
Every region and race has its own different ways of cooking dumplings,
饺子会因为土地及人种的不同 而有不同的烹饪方式
yet they all taste delicious.
但不管是哪一种都很好吃
R-Right!
对了！
It's just like us right now.
就像是现在的我们
Even though some things have changed, we're still ourselves.
就算稍微有些改变 但我们还是我们
We'll make it work.
一定会顺利的
That wraps things up nicely, doesn't it?
这样事情就算圆满了结了吧？
Only in your head.
那是你的错觉
Anyway, this place is odd.
不过这里还真是奇特
I wonder what it was.
到底是什么样的地方？
It's a defensive stronghold built by dwarves, right?
是矮人们所建的防卫地点之一吧？
Defensive?
防卫？
From when the elves and dwarves were at war.
在精灵和矮人间发生战争的时候
Didn't you learn about it in school?
你在学校没有学到吗？
They competed to develop more and more advanced technology,
双方争着让技术急速发展
which eventually led to a catastrophe.
结果导致大灾难的发生
Elves and dwarves are afraid of history repeating itself,
因此精灵及矮人担心会重蹈覆辙
which is why they're prickly about technology in the dungeon.
所以才对迷宫内的技术如此神经质
This dungeon, in particular, is where many cultures intersect,
尤其是这座迷宫 是各种文化发生冲突的地方
so I imagine we're going to have a lot of conflicts when elves step in.
不难想象介入时一定会发生不少纠纷
Yeah, a-about that.
关于那件事
If we run into trouble with the elves, you can do something about it, right?
如果精灵找我们茬的话 你有办法解决对吧？
Huh? Why me?
什么？为什么是我？
You said your mom worked at the court.
你妈妈不是在宫廷中工作吗？
Don't you have connections?
难道就没有认识相关人士吗？
W-Well…
这个嘛…
Now, now.
算了啦
Anyway, she's a half-foot now.
不管怎样 她现在是一个半身人
If anyone's going to negotiate with the elves, it's Senshi.
要和精灵交涉的话也是要由先西来做
I'll do what I can.
我会妥善处理的
Actually, we should keep searching for a way to revert back.
我们还是尽可能 持续找回复原状的方法吧
-Agreed.
-赞成
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻译：柯欣冉